{"tossups": [{"question": "This man served in a guerilla corps led by Vojislav Tankosi\u0107 [[VOY-ih-slahv tahn-KOH-sitch]], harassing Ottoman Turk occupiers in the early 20th century. An associate of this man named Nedeljko \u010cabrinovi\u0107 [[nee-DEHL-koh kah-BREE-noh-vitch]] failed to kill a noble target with a faulty hand grenade. While at a deli on the Latin Bridge, this assassin stopped a motorcade to fire his pistol at the Duchess of Hohenberg and her spouse. For the point, name this Bosnian Serb and member of the Black Hand who killed Archduke Franz Ferdinand.", "answer": "Gavrilo <b><u>Princip</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Richard Lander and Jean Rouche [[ZHANH ROOSH]] became the first to traverse the length of this river, using a 16-millimeter camera to record their 1946 journey. During his second expedition down this river, Mungo Park died at the Bussa Rapids. Agriculture on this river led to the rise of Djenn\u00e9-Djenno in what is now Mali. This river's modern name was given in 1550 by Berber geographer Leo Africanus. For the point, name this river which both ibn Batutta and Pliny believed connected to the Nile.", "answer": "<b><u>Niger</u></b> River (pronounced as either [[nee-ZHER]] or [[NAI-jer]], be lenient)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This Kurdish leader overthrew the Fatamid dynasty and survived several assassination attempts. This sultan established his own dynasty which was named for his father, Ayyub. Many centuries later, Hafez Assad commissioned a statue of this leader for the Citadel of Damascus. This man\u2019s victory at the Battle of Hattin [[hah-TEEN]], and his subsequent capture of Jerusalem, led to the Third Crusade. For the point, what sultan, famous for his wisdom and nobility, fought Richard the Lionheart at Acre [[AH-kruh]]?", "answer": "<b><u>Saladin</u></b> (or <b><u>Salah ad-Din</u></b> Yusuf)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1982, this future politician created the MBR-200, which evolved into the Movement for the Fifth Republic. In 1992, this man launched a failed coup to replace Carlos Andr\u00e9s P\u00e9rez with Rafael Caldera. Following the tenth anniversary of the Caracazo in 1999, this man drafted a new constitution granting himself additional presidential power, the abuse of which led him to be temporarily removed from office in 2002. Nicol\u00e1s Maduro succeeded, for the point, what longtime president of Venezuela who died in 2013?", "answer": "Hugo <b><u>Ch\u00e1vez</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Fred Wyman persuaded this leader to hold the \u201cRumble in the Jungle\u201d between Muhammad Ali and George Foreman to give his regime a national stage. With Chinese support, this man orchestrated an invasion of neighboring Angola which was repulsed by Castro-deployed Cuban paratroopers. This figure, who seized power from the Patrice Lumumba government, renamed Leopoldville to Kinshasa during his Authenticity Campaign. For the point, name this 20th century Congolese dictator who renamed his nation to Zaire.", "answer": "<b><u>Mobutu</u></b> Sese Seko (accept Sese <b><u>Seko</u></b>; accept Joseph-D\u00e9sir\u00e9 <b><u>Mobutu</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Robert Eisenman argued that this person was in the family of Herod the Great, as evidenced by their having written, \"Greet Herodion [[heh-ROH-dee-un]], my kinsman.\" This person received tutelage under Gamaliel [[guh-MAY-lee-uhl]], though he became a tentmaker instead of a rabbi. According to a Biblical account, this person participated in the stoning of Stephen before being blinded by a flash of light on the way to Damascus. For the point, name this first century Christian apostle, the traditional author of Ephesians [[eh-FEE-shuns]], Galatians [[gah-LAY-shuns]], and Romans.", "answer": "Apostle <b><u>Paul</u></b> (accept <b><u>Saul</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This leader broke decades of tradition by refusing to live in the \u00c7ankaya [[CHAHN-kai-yah]] Mansion, opting to live in a massive, illegally-built palace constructed in a national forest. This man labeled a 2013 corruption scandal targeting the Justice and Development Party a plot orchestrated by Fethullah G\u00fclen [[FETH-oo-lah goo-LEN]]. In 2016, the Peace at Home Committee allegedly launched a coup against this leader which included a blockade of the Bosporus Bridge. For the point, name this president of Turkey.", "answer": "Recep Tayyip <b><u>Erdo\u011fan</u></b> [[reh-DZEHP tai-YEEP EHR-duh-wahn]]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This party outlined its 1993 federal political platform in the Red Book, whose official title is <em>Creating Opportunity</em>. The Beauharnois [[boh-har-NWAH]] bribery scandal tainted the reputation of William Lyon Mackenzie King, a prime minister of this party. The TransCanada Pipeline Debate contributed to the defeat of this party's 1957 incumbent candidate, Louis St. Laurent [[SANH luh-RANH]], and the end of more than twenty years with this party in power. For the point, name this Canadian political party.", "answer": "<b><u>Liberal</u></b> Party of Canada", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In preparation to attack this country, the Bengal Native Infantry revolted in 1824's Barrackpore mutiny. Henry Godwin invaded this country in 1824, and Richard Cobden's pamphlet \"How Wars are Got Up in India\" explained how Britain took advantage of this country. George Orwell set \"Shooting an Elephant\" in this country whose Third Anglo War included British plans for invading on the Irrawaddy to end the Konbaung [[KOHN-BAHNG]] Dynasty. For the point, what is this Southeast Asian nation in which Aung San Suu Kyi [[AWNG SAHN SOO CHEE]] has fought for democracy?", "answer": "Republic of the Union of <b><u>Myanmar</u></b> (accept <b><u>Burma</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The daughter of Henry Liddell sold an original manuscript of this book for over fifteen thousand pounds at an auction at Sotheby\u2019s [[SUH-thuh-bees]] in 1926. Characters in this book, such as the pointy-chinned Duchess, were originally illustrated by <em>Punch</em> cartoonist John Tenniel. This story originated on a \"golden afternoon\" when a mathematician rowed from Oxford to Godstow in 1865, telling a story to Lorina, Edith, and Alice along the way. For the point, name this fantastical children\u2019s book by Lewis Carroll.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Alice in Wonderland</u></b></em> (or <em><b><u>Alice\u2019s Adventures in Wonderland</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This island's Valley of the Temples contains the ancient Temples of Concordia and Heracles. Ancient residents of this island built the Necropolis of Pantalica [[PAHN-tah-LAI-kah]]. During the rule of the Kingdom in the Sun, invaders built the Norman Palace on this island. Archimedes legendarily built a heat ray to defend this island's city of Syracuse, and the mafia originated near this island's city of Palermo. For the point, name this largest island in the Mediterranean Sea, less than two miles from the tip of the Italian \"boot.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Sicily</u></b> (or <b><u>Sicilia</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Fernando Terry founded this country's Popular Action party, and ICJ head Jos\u00e9 Luis Bustamante y Rivero served as this country's president from 1945 to 1948. Alan Garc\u00eda, a former president of this country, committed suicide in 2019 before he could be arrested for his involvement in the Odebrecht [[OH-duh-brekt]] scandal. President Alberto Fujimori carried out a self-coup in 1992 to solidify his power in this country. For the point, name this South American country whose presidents govern from the House of Pizarro in Lima.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Peru</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "During a battle at this location, James Abercrombie's numerically superior army was forced to retreat after a costly frontal attack against troops under the Marquis de Montcalm. Arthur St. Clair and Philip Schuyler [[SKY-ler]] were court-martialed after failing to defend this location against John Burgoyne. With help from Ethan Allen, Benedict Arnold captured this fort, allowing Henry Knox to take this fort's cannons and use them to end the Siege of Boston. For the point, name this fort near Lake Champlain which changed hands several times in the 18th century.", "answer": "Fort <b><u>Ticonderoga</u></b> (accept Fort <b><u>Carillon</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "It's not Cyprus, but this state was to be taken in Operation Attila. The last members of this regime surrendered at the Sigmaringen [[sig-mah-RIN-gehn]] Enclave. The members of this regime were subject to the Legal Purge and \"national degradation,\" through which they lost civil rights. This regime's SOL, which Joseph Darnand created, was once headed by Pierre Laval. This regime arrested Jews in the Vel' d'hiv [[vehl DEEV]] Roundup. Philippe Petain [[peh-TAHN]] led this state which ended the Third Republic in 1940. For the point, name this French collaborationist regime which aided the Nazis.", "answer": "<b><u>Vichy</u></b> France (accept <b><u>French State</u></b>; accept <b><u>\u00c9tat fran\u00e7ais</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "At the burial place of this man's wife, Daniyal constructed a pleasure garden in Buhanpur. This man's daughter, Jahanara Begum, nearly died from severe burns but survived to care for this man in his final years of confinement. This man's brother, Khusrau [[KOOS-ro]], unsuccessfully attempted to overthrow their father, Jahangir, in 1606. Ustad Ahmad Lahori constructed the Red Fort for this man, whose son Aurangzeb [[oh-RAHNG-zeb]] seized power after declaring this man incompetent. For the point, name this Mughal emperor who built the Taj Mahal.", "answer": "Shah <b><u>Jahan</u></b> (or Shahab-ud-din Muhammad <b><u>Khurram</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "When a plane carrying this country\u2019s leader, Juv\u00e9nal Habyarimana [[hah-byah-ree-MAH-nah]], was shot down, a cryptic order commanded one ethnic group to \u201cCut down the tall trees,\u201d igniting a mass murder in this country. This country's Volcanoes National Park was the base for Dian Fossey and is home to the largest Mountain Gorilla population in the world. This mountainous country elected Paul Kagame [[kah-GAH-meh]] as president in 2000 and gained its independence from Burundi in 1962. For the point, what is this central African country?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Rwanda</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Kingdom of Candia was an overseas colony of this state, who lost it to the Ottoman Empire during the Cretan War. Boniface [[BAH-nee-fahss]] of Montferrat sold Crete to this state which also controlled the Peloponnese and Cyprus. This state became a flourishing center for trade in the 13th century following the elimination of pirates along the Dalmatian coast of the Adriatic Sea. For the point, name this medieval city-state ruled by a Doge [[DOHZH]] and represented by the Banner of St. Mark.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Venice</u></b> (accept <b><u>Venetian</u></b> Republic; accept La <b><u>Serenissima</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 2016, the leader of this country's Liberal Party and the prime minister, Erna Solberg, were both caught playing Pokemon GO during official meetings. This country, the site of a 2011 terror event on its island of Ut\u00f8ya [[OOH-tau-wah]], also experienced a landslide in its village of Ask [[AHSK]] in 2020. The first Secretary General of the United Nations was from this country whose parliament is known as the <em>Storting</em>. For the point, name this country whose vast oil wealth is managed from Oslo.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Norway</u></b> (or <b><u>Norge</u></b>; or <b><u>Noreg</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This German composed four different overtures for his only opera, in which a faithful wife pretends to be a man so she can visit her husband in prison. After Napoleon declared himself Emperor, this musician scratched out the dedication on the title page of his Third symphony. Among this man\u2019s 32 piano sonatas are the <em>Appasionata</em>, the <em>Path\u00e9tique</em>, and the <em>Moonlight</em>. For the point, what composer wrote the <em>Eroica</em> Symphony and the opera <em>Fidelio</em>?", "answer": "Ludwig van <b><u>Beethoven</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In 2019, Phillip Beale attempted to prove that ships of this civilization were able to sail across the Atlantic Ocean. According to Herodotus, this thalassocratic civilization circumnavigated Africa around 600 BCE with a sponsorship from an Egyptian pharaoh. Murex snails were once used to create a valuable purple dye named for this civilization's city of Tyre. For the point, name this ancient civilization which founded the city of Carthage and distributed the world's oldest alphabet throughout the Mediterranean.", "answer": "The <b><u>Phoenicia</u></b>ns", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This creator of <em>The Cliffs at Etretat</em> [[eht-reh-TAH]] loved to paint \u201c<em>en plein air</em>\u201d [[anh plen-EHR]], or outdoors. This man often worked on several paintings of the same subject, such as his Rouen [[roo-ANH]] Cathedral Series, throughout the day, switching canvases as the light changed. Later in life, with his eyesight declining, this Frenchman painted gigantic canvases of aquatic flowers near his home in Giverny [[zhi-vehr-NEE]]. For the point, name this French Impressionist who painted several series of haystacks and water lilies.", "answer": "Claude <b><u>Monet</u></b> [[moh-NAY]]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man took Grimoald [[GRIM-wald]] III hostage, forcing Arechis [[ah-REH-kiss]] II of Benevento to pledge his loyalty. After defeating Desiderius during the Siege of Pavia, this man declared himself King of the Lombards. The seizure of several papal cities forced Pope Adrian I to ask this man to enforce the policies of his father, Pepin the Short, and to assist in their return. For the point, name this Frankish ruler whom Pope Leo III crowned Holy Roman Emperor on Christmas Day in the year 800.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlemagne</u></b> (accept <b><u>Charles the Great</u></b>; accept <b><u>Charles I</u></b>; accept <b><u>Carolus</u></b> <b><u>Magnus</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Major Huda's men killed Jamil Uddin Ahmad in this country, leaving Amin Ahmed Chowdhury [[CHOH-duh-ree]] to discover the outcome. This country's history includes the Second Revolution, which ended the BAKSAL political front. Despite A. F. M. Mohitul [[MOH-hee-tuhl]] Islam's attempt to identify the killers, this country's Indemnity Act allowed some of the assassins of Sheikh Mujibur Rahman [[MOO-jee-buhr RAHK-mahn]] to go free. Once led by the Awami League, for the point, what is this country which fought Pakistan for independence?", "answer": "People's Republic of <b><u>Bangladesh</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's life is the basis of a play by Bertolt Brecht [[BREHKT]]. A NASA spacecraft named for this man explored the moons of Jupiter, which this man once named the Medicean [[meh-dih-SEE-un]] stars after his Florentine patrons. This scientist studied sunspots and the rings of Saturn, and after this man championed heliocentrism, the Catholic Church forced him into house arrest. For the point, what Florentine scientist supposedly dropped two cannonballs from the Tower of Pisa?", "answer": "<b><u>Galileo</u></b> Galilei (accept <b><u>Galilei</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "This ruler was granted the Cautionary Towns as security for repayment. Under this ruler, the Leicester [[LEH-ster]] Expedition landed at Flushing. Frederick II of Denmark offered to close \"The Sound\" to assist this ruler if Philip II of Spain refused his aid. This ruler signed the Treaty of Nonsuch [[NUN-such]] and provided aid to rebels under the House of Orange. This ruler led England to victory against Spain during the Anglo-Spanish War. For the point, name this Tudor monarch of England sometimes called the \"Virgin Queen.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Elizabeth I</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man played twelve seasons at the beginning of his career in Milwaukee and two more in the same city for a different team at the end of his 23-year career. This slugger ended his career with 3,771 hits and still holds the record for most career RBIs. Britt Gaston and Cliff Courtenay risked arrest to accompany this man as he circled the bases to complete his best-known achievement in Atlanta. For the point, what twenty-time All-Star, nicknamed \u201cThe Hammer,\u201d broke Babe Ruth\u2019s career home run record in 1973?", "answer": "Henry \"Hank\" <b><u>Aaron</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The alleged poisoning of this man's mother, Elena Glinskaya, led to the beginning of his reign at the age of eight. This man relinquished his claims on Astrakhan to make peace with Khan Devlet I Giray of Crimea. This man fought the Livonian War and forced an archbishop to ride backwards when he used his <em>Oprichniki</em> [[oh-pritch-NEE-kee]] to massacre Novgorod's citizens. This man died while playing chess with Bogdan Belsky, ushering in the Time of Troubles. For the point, name this first Tsar of All the Russias, often thought of as mentally unstable.", "answer": "<b><u>Ivan the Terrible</u></b> (or <b><u>Ivan IV</u></b> Vasilyevich)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Dan Desdunes [[deh-DOON]] was meant to be the plaintiff of this case but failed to get himself arrested. Albion W. Tourg\u00e9e [[toor-ZHAY]] is said to have introduced the metaphor \"color blind justice\" while litigating this case. John Marshall Harlan was this case's lone dissenter on the U.S. Supreme Court, arguing that the Louisiana Separate Car Act of 1890 was unconstitutional. For the point, name this 1896 case which affirmed the doctrine of \"separate but equal\" later overturned by <em>Brown v. Board of Education</em>.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Plessy</u></b> v. Ferguson</em> (accept <em>Homer A.</em> <em><b><u>Plessy</u></b> v. John H. Ferguson</em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This language included an AB [[AY-BEE]] form with a unique phonetic system as found in the Katherine Group. The \"estuary\" form of this language features yod-coalescence. This language emerged as the Chancery Standard, and in 1362, this language was required in courts under the \"Pleading in [this language] Act.\" This language contains duplicate words that were taken from Old Norman, including \"beef\" and \"mutton.\" For the point, name this language used in writing by Geoffrey Chaucer.", "answer": "Middle <b><u>English</u></b> (do not accept \"Old English\")", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {"question": "Ambrose King called this city a \"synarchy.\" This city's Possession Street marks a naval landing by Edward Belcher. The Forbes family made its fortune trading in this city with companies like Dent & Co. and Jardine Matheson. Claude Maxwell MacDonald secured a lease on this city, connected to the mainland by the Kowloon-Canton Railway, for what he thought was \"as good as forever.\" For the point, name this former British colony which was obtained by the British at the end of the First Opium War and returned to China in 1997.", "answer": "<b><u>Hong Kong</u></b> Special Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China (accept <b><u>HKSAR</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The Treaty of Corbeil [[kor-BAY]], signed eleven years before the start of this war, led Robert the Bruce to pledge support for France. Twenty years passed between this war\u2019s last battle at Castillon [[kas-tee-YOHN]] and a formal peace treaty. Foot soldiers on one side of this war were killed while mooning archers in a taunt at the Battle of Cr\u00e9cy. At this war's conclusion, England lost all mainland European territories except for Calais [[kah-LAY]]. For the point, name this war in which Joan of Arc relieved the Siege of Orleans [[or-lay-AHN]].", "answer": "The <b><u>Hundred Years\u2019</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}